Guide to the Frank Chamberlin Porter Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Frank Chamberlin Porter Papers
1886-1967
1886-1940
RG 119
Yale University Divinity School Library
4.5
(10 boxes)
Correspondence, notes, and writings document Porter's life and work. Frank Chamberlin Porter (1859-1946) was Winkley Professor of Biblical Theology at the Yale Divinity School from 1891 to 1927.
Porter, Frank Chamberlin, 1859-1946
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1859 Born
1880 B.A., Beloit
1883 M.A., Beloit
1886 B.D., Yale
1889 Ph.D., Yale
1889-1891 Instructor in Biblical Theology
1891-1927 Winkley Professor of Biblical Theology, Yale
1895-1925 Librarian of the Yale Divinity School
1897 D.D., Beloit
1927-1946 Professor Emeritus
1928-1929 Nathaniel W. Taylor Lecturer
1931 D.D., Yale
1946 Died
Scope and Contents
I. Biographical Documentation
II. Correspondence
III. Notes
IV. Writings
V. Printed Material
VI. Personal Items and Memorabilia
Correspondence, notes, writings, and collected material document Porter's life and work.
Arrangement
I. Biographical Documentation
II. Correspondence
III. Notes
IV. Writings
V. Printed Material
VI. Personal Items and Memorabilia
Educators; Porter, Frank Chamberlin, 1859-1946; Yale University -- Faculty
- Biographical Documentation, Series I
  - Incl. from The Beloit Alumnus (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1894-1940; Series II
  - Chronologically arranged letters to/from Porter, 1894-1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Addendum: incl. letters to/from Charles C. Torrey, Benjamin Bacon; typed excerpts of letters from colleagues; typed copy of letter from H. Richard Niebuhr to Roland Bainton re. Porter, 1923-1938 (Box 7, Folder 88)
- Notes, Series III
  - Notes written by Porter; arranged alphabetically by topic, followed by folders of miscellaneous notes. (Box 1, Folder 3-16)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 4)
  - Bound volume of notes taken by H. R. Miles from lectures delivered by Porter: New Testament Theology, Old Testament Theology, The Fourth Gospel as Related to Alexandrianism, 1891-1893 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Approximately 2,000 pages of notes, which include Porter's notes on NT Theology, his "Religion of the Spirit", various jottings, notes on his colleague Benjamin W. Bacon, class outlines, etc. (Box 7, Folder 89-94)
  - Miscellaneous unorganized notes (Box 8, Folder 95)
  - Notes and manuscript drafts for a book, Chapters I- X (Box 9, Folder 96)
- Writings, 1896; Series IV
  - "The Apocrypha" from The Biblical World, pp. 272-279, 1896 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - "The Bearing of Historical Studies on the Religious Use of the Bible" from The Harvard Theological Review, pp. 253-276, 1909 Jul (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Review of The Book of Jubilees in Current Literature, 1888 Apr (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - "Lews Orsmond Brastow" - memorial address, 1913 Jan (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - "Does Paul Claim to Have Known the Historical Jesus" from Journal of Biblical Literature, pp. 257-275, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - "The Historical and Spiritual Understanding of the Bible" from Education for Christian Service, pp. 20-48, 1922 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - The Ideals of Seminaries and the Needs of the Churches, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - "Inquiries Concerning the Divinity of Christ" from American Journal of Theology, pp. 9-29, 1904 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - "An Interview with New Testament Scholars" from The Biblical World (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - "The Jewish Literature of New Testament Times: Why Should it be Studied?" from The Old and New Testament Student, pp. pp. 71-78, 142-151, 1889 Aug (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - "Judaism in New Testament Times" from The Journal of Religion, pp. 30-62, 1928 Jan (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Review of The Messianic Hope in the New Testament by S. Mathews from Am. J. of Theology, pp. 111-115 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Review of Philo-Judaeus by J. Drummond from New Englander, pp. 127-139, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - "The Place of Apocalyptical Conceptions in the Thought of Paul" from J. of Bib. Lit., pp. 183-204, 1922 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - "The Place of the Sacred Book in the Christian Religion" (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - "The Pre-existence of the Soul in the book of Wisdom and in the Rabbinical Writings" from Old Testament and Semitic Studies, pp. 205-270, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - "Princeton Theology" (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - "Prophecy and Apocalypse" from The Biblical World, pp. 36-41, 1899 Jul (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - "The Psalms of the Prophets" from The Biblical World, pp. 167-176, 1894 Sep (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - "The Problem of Things New and Old in the Beginnings of Christianity -- Primitive Christianity and Judaism: A Symposium" from J. of Bib. Lit., pp. 1-23, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - "The Religious and Historical Uses of the Bible", 1894 Jun (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - "Religious Fellowship, Its Basis, Bounds, and Banes" - address before the New York State Conference of Religion, 1914 Jun (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - "The Religious Ideas of the Book of Ecclesiasticus I and II, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - "The Religous Ideas of the First Book of Maccabees", 1892 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - "Revelation, Book of" from Hastings Dicionary of the Bible, 1902 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - "The Sayings of Jesus about the First and the Last" from J. of Bib. Lit., pp. 97-110, 1906 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - "A Source-book of Judaism in New Testament Times -- Critical Notes" from Am. J. of Theology (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - "The Spirits in Prison -- a Neglected Theory Reconsidered" from New Englander and Yale Review, 1888 Aug (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - "The Spirit of God in the Minds of Men" - address before the N.Y. State Conference of Religion, 1903 Oct (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - "The Yecer Hara: a study in the Jewish Doctrine of Sin" from Biblical and Semitic Studies, pp. 93-156 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - "The Spirit of Christianity and the Jesus of History" (typescript) (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - "The Bible and the Religion of the Spirit" (typescript) (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - "The Place of the New Testament in the Christian Religion (typescript), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - "Word and Spirit in Paul" (typescript) (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - "A Statement of Christian Belief", 1895 (Box 6, Folder 80a)
  - "A System of Abbreviations", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 80a)
  - "Things Greater and Less in the Bible" from Yale Divinity Quarterly March 1911 (Box 6, Folder 80a)
- Printed Material, Series V
  - War poetry and notes (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1886-1887, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Material related to Yale (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 86)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series VI
  - Including license, cards, photographs (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Photographs (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Family expense book, 1908-1916 (Box 10, Folder 97)
  - "The Anecdotage of the Grandmother of the Seminary" - writings by Mrs. Frank C. Porter (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - "The Porter Home in Beloit and Related Note"; letter from Porter's son to Jonathan Preus including biographical information about Porter, 1967, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 76)